Guide to the Sir Walter Scott Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Sir Walter Scott collection
1803-1831
GEN MSS 266
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
2
(2 boxes) + 4 volumes
The collection consists primarily of letters from Scott to various correspondents, including James Ballantyne, John Wilson Croker, and Mary Ann (Watts) Hughes; and writings by Scott, including The House of Aspen and The Talisman.
Other Storage Formats: 4 volumes
Scott, Walter, 1771-1832
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ongoing collection of documents acquired by gift and purchase from various sources. Type of accession (gift or purchase) and date of acquisition is noted in the box-and-folder list. For further information, consult the appropriate curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
This finding aid encompasses accessions of single manuscripts and small groups of manuscripts and other papers, by or pertaining to Sir Walter Scott, which the library has chosen to group and list as an artifical collection.
English literature -- 19th century; Ballantyne, James, 1772-1833; Croker, John Wilson, 1780-1857; Hughes, Mary Ann Watts, 1770?-1853; Scott, Walter, 1771-1832
- Letters by Sir Walter Scott, 1821 Sep 7; Series I
  - ALS to James Ballantyne, 1821 Sep 7 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Accompanied by original agreement between James Ballantyne and Constable & Co. for Quentin Durward dated 1821 Sep 3 and by engraving of Sir Walter Scott. Gift, 1973.
  - ALS to [Mr. Balmanno], Abbotsford, 1827 Aug 2 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Accompanied by typescript. Robert Balmanno was secretary of the Artist's Fund, and publisher.
  - ALS to Mr. Blackwood, Abbotsford, [1824 May?] (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Purchase, 1952.
  - ALS to [Sir Egerton Brydges?], n.d. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Gift, 1953.
  - ALS to George Bullock, n.y. Apr 1 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Purchase, 1956.
  - ALS to Messrs. Cadell & Davis, Edinburgh, 1801 Dec 26 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    With 2 LS with initials C & D, London, 1801 Dec 29, 1802 Feb 23 on p. 2 and 3, with portrait. Purchase, 1959.
  - 2 ALS to John Clarke-Whitfield, Edinburgh, 1811, 1816 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Accompanied by a manuscript transcript of both letters. Gift, 1943.
  - ALS to [Messrs. R & J] Cockburn, Castle Street, n.y. Jun 28 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Gift, 1944
  - 30 ALS to John Wilson Croker, 1810-1831
    Bound by Wallis in green full morocco. Accompanied by portrait and printed memoir.
    Immediate Source of Acquisition
    Gift, 1927.
  - ALS to William J. East, 1820 Jan (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Gift, 1943.
  - ALS to James Ellis, Edinburgh, 1814 Dec 15 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Describing his northern tour, and inquiring for the author of the Reedwater minstrel. The author of the Reedwater Minstrel was Rob Roxby. Gift, 1941.
  - ALS to William Erskine, Abbotsford, 1821 Sep 29 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Gift, 1926
  - ALS to [John Gibson?], Abbotsford, 1826 Apr 20 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    One of Scott's three trustees, concerning publication and financial matters. Purchase, 1942.
  - Letter to Lady Katherine Halket, Edinburgh, 1819 Jun (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Purchase, 1958.
  - ALS to [Matthew Weld] Hartstonge, Abbotsford, 1814 Jul 18 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Accompanied by a carbon typescript. From the William Harris Arnold collection. Gift, 1944.
  - AL to Miss Hayman, Edinburgh, [1807] Nov 10 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Signature cut off. Purchase, 1952.
  - 4 ALS to Richard Heber, Edinburgh, 1805-13 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Purchase, 1965.
  - AL, signed with initials, to [James] Hogg, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Removed from James Hogg's Poetic Mirror, London, 1816 Purchase, 1930.
  - ALS to Thomas Hood (Bookseller), 1823 Sep 26 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Gift, 1954.
  - 42 ALS and 2 AL to Mrs. Mary Ann (Watts) Hughes, various places, [1807?]-31 (Box 1, Folder 19-25)
    Accompanied by a typewritten copy of "Extracts etc. not printed in Letters and recollections of Sir Walter Scott " Purchase, 1952.
  - ALS to [William] Millar, the bookseller, [Edinburgh?], 1808 Mar 25 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    Gift, 1936.
  - ALS to Sir Woodbine Parish, Edinburgh, [1803?] Dec 14 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    Purchase, 1955.
  - ALS to Robert Pitcairn, Abbotsford, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 28)
    Gift, 1926.
  - ALS to Henry Raeburn, n.y. May 8 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    Gift, 1957.
  - ALS to Owen Rees, the publisher, Edinburgh, [1808] Jun 9 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - ALS to John Richardson, Abbotsford, [1817] Sep 22 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    Mentions a visit from Washington Irving. Accompanied by typewritten transcript. Purchase, 1938.
  - Letter to Spottiswood & Robertson, Solicitors, with a fragment in Scott's hand, 1812 Jul 2
    Inserted in Scott's personal copy of the British Bankruptcy and Jury Acts, published in 1814 and 1815. The Acts are bound together, with blank leaves between, with manuscript forms of Interlocutors in Sequestration, not in Scott's hand, but with corrections by Scott.
    Related Archival Materials note
    See: Volume 1
  - ALS to Richard [Robert] Surtees, Abbotsford, [1828] Apr 1 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    "Diccon the Reaver" mentioned in this letter refers to Surtees' poem "The reever's penance." Gift, 1926.
  - ALS to Mr. John Williams, Jermyn Street, n.y. Mar 24 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    With manuscript notes on Scott and Williams. Purchase, 1956.
  - ALS to "Sir", Abbotsford, 1821 Nov 3 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    With typewritten transcript, engraved portrait and clipped signature. Gift, 1955.
  - ALS to an unnamed correspondent, Edinburgh, n.y. Dec 4 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    Purchase, 1960.
  - ALS to unidentified recipient, Abbotsford, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 36)
    Gift, 1950.
  - Letter in the third person in an unidentified hand extending a dinner invitation to Mr. Sharpe., [1817?] (Box 1, Folder 37)
- Writings by Sir Walter Scott, Series II
  The House of Aspen, a tragedy founded upon a German Story
  - The original manuscript on paper, written in the hand of an amanuensis, but with numerous corrections in the author's autograph. The whole of the fifth act is in Walter Scott's hand.
    Bound in red morocco, by Orrock, with the Marquess of Lothian's arms. Purchase, 1932.
    See: Volume 2
  - Manuscript in an unidentified hand, with a few corrections by Scott.
    Paper watermarked 1799. Autograph of O. Rees; subsequently in the library of Dr. Thomas Rees. Bound in brown calf. Gift, 1954.
    See: Volume 3
  - Review of Charles Maturin's novel Women; or Pour et Contre, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 38)
    Autograph manuscript. Inlaid and bound with the manuscript is the printed review, as it appeared in the Edinburgh Review, June 1818. Gift, 1926.
  - "Sir Walter Scott and Mr. Wilkie", galley proof of a "Letter from Sir Walter Scott to Sir Adam Ferguson...", 1827 Oct 15 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    At head of caption in Scott's hand: "Morning Chronicle, Monday 15 Oct. 1827 and one correction in the text. With ALS to Mr. Balmanno, Abbotsford, 1827 Aug 2; heavily corrected proof of the same article (with slight changes) as it appeared in The Bijou, London 1828; printed copy of article from The Bijou; typescript of Scott's additions and corrections; and a portrait of Sir Walter Scott. Purchase, 1943.
  - The Talisman, 1825
    Page proofs with autograph manuscript corrections and additions; with criticisms and comments in the hand of the printer, James Ballantyne, and Scott's replies.
    Bound in are 6 ALS to James Ballantyne, [1825?]. Bookplate of Charles George Milnes Gaskell. Bound in brown russia. Gift, 1952.
    See: Volume 4
  - "The Violet", n.d. (Box 1, Folder 40)
    Autograph manuscript poem. Mounted with fragment in 16th century Italic hand, labeled "Phil Melancthon, cut from margin of his copy of Plutarch's Lives."
  - "The Visionary No. III", n.d. (Box 1, Folder 41)
    Autograph manuscript, bound, with notes and corrections. Purchase, 1939.
  - Waverley, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 42)
    Fragment (about 60 words) of the autograph manuscript. Accompanied by another fragment with note, "Thomas Thomson Esq. from W Scott" in the latter's hand, and a photograph of a portrait of Scott.
  - Penciled memorandum of directions for a trip to the Trossachs (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Page of manuscript describing a battle between the Saracens and Christians (Box 1, Folder 44)
- Other Papers, 1805-06; Series III
  - "Particulars of charges for Messrs. Constables Proportions of the different editions 'Lay of the Last Minstrel'", 1805-06 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    Manuscript accounts in an unidentified hand.
  - Typewritten list of autograph letters, manuscripts and miscellaneous papers of Scott that comprised the collection of his attorney, John Gibson and purchased by Hugh Walpole from John Howell. (Box 1, Folder 46)
    With 2 TLS to Wilmarth S. Lewis from John Howell, 1952. Gift, 1952
  - Manuscript fragment, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 47)
- Volumes, 1812 Jul 2
  - Letter to Spottiswood & Robertson, Solicitors, with a fragment in Scott's hand, 1812 Jul 2 (Box Volume 1)
    Inserted in Scott's personal copy of the British Bankruptcy and Jury Acts, published in 1814 and 1815. The Acts are bound together, with blank leaves between, with manuscript forms of Interlocutors in Sequestration, not in Scott's hand, but with corrections by Scott. Gift, 1926.
  - The House of Aspen, a tragedy founded upon a German Story (Box Volume 2)
    - The original manuscript on paper, written in the hand of an amenuensis, but with numerous corrections in the author's autograph. The whole of the fifth act is in Walter Scott's hand.
    - Manuscript in an unidentified hand, with a few corrections by Scott. (Box Volume 3)
  - The Talisman, 1825 (Box Volume 4)
    Bound in are 6 ALS to James Ballantyne, [1825?]. Bookplate of Charles George Milnes Gaskell. Bound in brown russia.
- Oversize, 1810-1831
  - 30 ALS to John Wilson Croker, 1810-1831 (Box 2, Folder 48)
    Bound by Wallis in green full morocco. Accompanied by portrait and printed memoir. Gift, 1927.